Guide to the Harold T. Parker Papers, 1914-2002 UA.29.02.0009
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Harold T. Parker papers
1914-2002
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Parker, Harold Talbot, 1907-2002
UA.29.02.0009
24.5 Linear Feet
Harold T. Parker taught history at Duke University from 1939-1977; he specialized in modern European history, European intellectual history and 19th century Europe. This collection contains material concerning Parker's experiences as a faculty member at Duke University, a soldier in World War II and as an author. The papers include correspondence, including v-mail, along with diaries, volumes, memoranda, reports, speeches, articles, photographs, essays, book drafts and other records.
Access Restrictions
Access restricted. Some materials in this collection include student records. In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Contact Research Services for more information.
Provenance
The Harold T. Parker Papers were received by the University Archives as a transfer starting in 1977.
Biographical Note
Harold T. Parker taught history at Duke University; he specialized in modern European history, European intellectual history and 19th century Europe. Parker was born near Cincinnati, Ohio on December 26, 1907. He received his undergraduate and doctoral degrees from University of Chicago in 1928 and 1934 respectively. He began teaching at Duke University in 1939 and retired in 1977, although he continued to teach after his retirement as a professor emeritus. His career at Duke was interrupted during World War II, when he served in the Pacific Theater. Parker was known for his teaching excellence according to one of his obituaries, and was awarded the Annual Distinguished Teaching Award by the National Association of Schools and Colleges of the United Methodist church in 1973. In addition to being a professor, Parker published several books including The Cult of Antiquity and the French Revolutionaries (1937) and Three Napoleonic Battles (1944). He was also a longstanding member of St. Philip's Episcopal Church in Durham, NC and published a history of the church in 1996. Harold T. Parker passed away in 2002.
Collection Overview
This collection contains material concerning Parker's experiences as a faculty member at Duke University, a soldier in World War II and as an author. The papers include correspondence, including v-mail, along with diaries, volumes, memoranda, reports, speeches, articles, photographs, essays, book drafts and other records. The volume titles include Back Load and Sky Train, which are histories of troop carrier forces in the South Pacific during World War II.
Duke University. Dept. of History; Duke University -- Faculty; World War, 1939-1945 -- England -- Personal narratives, English
- Correspondence, including war letters, and notes, 1914-1944 (Box 1)
- Selected schoolwork, grade school – graduate school, 1917-1931 (Box 1)
- Photographs, 1907-1918 (Box 1)
- Life chronologies, autobiographical essay (Box 1)
- Book: Sky Train (Box 1)
- Correspondence, including war letters, and notes, 1941-1969 (Box 2)
- Photographs, circa 1970s-1998 (Box 2)
- Miscellaneous papers, 1971-1998 (Box 2)
- Collections of articles (Box 2)
- Correspondence/war letters, 1942-1945 (Box 3)
- Addresses made by Parker, 1966-1994 (Box 3)
- Addresses on Parker as teacher, 1995 (Box 3)
- Essays, autobiographical writings, 1980, 1995 (Box 3)
- Personal papers, essays, notes, 1917-undated (Box 4)
- V-mail, 1943-1945 (Box 4)
- Books: Back Load, Sky Train (Box 4)
- Photographs (Box 4)
- Correspondence, including scholarly articles/papers sent to Parker for his review/critique/pleasure, some with Parker's responses/annotations, 1993-2001 and undated (Box 5)
- Conference materials – programs, programs, notes, correspondence, copies of articles from proceedings, 1989, 1992, 1994 (Box 5)
- Photocopies of articles – some with notes by Parker, some grouped in folders by subject 1952-1998, bulk 1996-1998 (Box 5)
- Articles, book chapters, book reviews, presentations written by Parker – some with related correspondence 1997, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
- Church and Synagogue Library Association materials – correspondence, notes, book reviews 1988-1991 (Box 5)
- Softcover books on French Army (Box 5)
- Genealogy notes and correspondence (Box 5)
- April 1962 Duke Alumni Register, in which Parker appears (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous magazines and articles, 2000-2001 (Box 5)
- Miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 5)
- 1906 Hughes High School Annual, Cincinnati, Ohio (Box 6)
- Scholarly articles/papers sent to Parker for his review/critique/pleasure; some with correspondence, 1998-2000 (Box 6)
- Photocopies of articles/book segments, some with notes by Parker, 1963, 1970, undated (Box 6)
- Diary, 1983 (Box 6)
- Conference materials – presentation and misc. notes, 1994 (Box 6)
- University Prints (art reproductions), with some notes by Parker (Box 6)
- Printout of 1967 Ph.D. dissertation by J.M.P. McErlean (re: Napoleon) (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous correspondence, 1999 (Box 6)
- Miscellaneous notes, mostly grouped in labeled envelopes; some with related books, undated (Box 6)
- Envelopes (usually labeled) full of notes, some with related books and photocopies of articles, 1969-1976, undated (Box 7)
- Paper written by Parker, with related photocopies (Box 7)
- Prints from the Company of Military Historians, circa 1986, 1988 (Box 7)
- Mrs. Parker's 1967 tax return (Box 7)
- Envelopes (usually labeled) full of notes, some with related books and photocopies of articles, undated (Box 8)
- Book drafts, presentations written by Parker – some with notes by Parker, 1999, undated (Box 8)
- Correspondence, including scholarly articles/papers sent to Parker for his review/critique/pleasure, circa 1990s-2001 (Box 8)
- Photocopies of articles, 1946-2000, undated (Box 8)
- Misc. notes, circa 1990s-2001, undated (Box 8)
- Photocopy of 1818 book on Napoleon (Box 8)
- Journal volume, book inscribed to Parker (Box 8)
- Correspondence, including scholarly articles/papers sent to Parker for his review/critique/pleasure, 1983-1999 (Box 9)
- Photocopies of articles, 1985-1987, undated (Box 9)
- Misc. notes and notebooks, some in labeled folders/envelopes, including daily meditations, 1972-1975, evolution as teacher, images for autobiography, circa 1970s-1998, undated (Box 9)
- Mrs. Parker's insurance and financial information, papers and reviews she wrote, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 9)
- Envelopes (usually labeled) full of misc. notes including autobiography, farm papers, house, undated (Box 10)
- Medical correspondence, 1969, circa 1990s, undated (Box 10)
- Personal journals, 1919-1921, 1981-1982, undated (Box 10)
- Family passports (Box 10)
- Photographs, slides (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous notes, 1973; 2000-2001; undated (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous journals, magazines, and photocopied articles and book on Napoleon, 1986; 2000-2001; undated (Box 10)
- Mrs. Parker's Ph.D. dissertation, 1952 (Box 10)
- 1910 Miami Bulletin, by S. Chester Parker (Box 10)
- Misc. photocopies, articles, notes, correspondence; some in labeled folders/envelopes (dates noted include 1979, '90s, 2000-02) (Box 11)
- Photocopies of articles, book chapters written by Parker, circa 1965-1990s (Box 11)
- Photographs (Box 11)
- Baby shoes (Box 11)
- Envelopes (usually labeled) full of misc. notes, some with correspondence, undated (Box 12)
  Scope and Contents note
  Material in boxes 12 and 13 were originally in a container labeled lectures/intellectual history.
- 7 envelopes (usually labeled) full of misc. notes, plus some loose notes, undated (Box 13)
- Other envelopes (usually labeled) full of notes, some with related photocopies of articles, undated (Box 13)
- Correspondence, 1999-2002 (Box 13)
- Photocopies of articles, 1971-1983 (Box 13)
- Misc. publications, 2002 (Box 13)
- Misc. notes, articles, student papers (Box 13)
- Insurance documents (Box 13)
- Papers, articles, reviews, correspondence, notes written by Parker (had been stored in suitcase), circa 1952-1990s (Box 14)
- Folder of copied correspondence, (had been stored in suitcase), 1940-1952 (Box 14)
- Savannah paper and correspondence, (had been stored in suitcase), 1934-1993 (Box 14)
- Manuscript of World War II book, with no title page or date (had been stored in suitcase) (Box 14)
- Correspondence, including scholarly articles/papers sent to Parker for his review/critique/pleasure (Box 14)
- Portraits of Napoleon (slides, prints) (Box 14)
- Misc. publications and photocopies of articles on Napoleon, 1978-1979, undated (Box 14)
- Misc. notes, some in labeled folders/envelopes, undated (Box 14)
- Correspondence, including scholarly articles/papers sent to Parker for his review/critique/pleasure, 1990-1998 (Box 15)
- Misc. notes, papers and prints on Napoleon, undated (Box 15)
- Genealogy notes, diaries, including pictures and correspondence, circa 1910-20s (Box 15)
- Misc. newspapers, 1963, 1996-1999) (Box 15)
- 2 pieces broken jewelry (Box 15)
- Photocopies of Napoleonic material written by Parker, circa 1957-1990s (Box 16)
- Correspondence, 1986-2000 (Box 16)
- Photographs, 2000 (Box 16)
- Misc. notes, some in labeled envelopes, 2000, undated (Box 16)
- Photocopy of Parker's The Bureau of Commerce in 1781, 1979 (Box 16)
- WWII diary, addition from Robert W. Brown, 1941-1942 (Box 16)
- Correspondence between Parker and Dr. Jane K. Burton (Box 17)
- Burton's writings about Parker (Box 17)
- Parker's reviews for the South Atlantic Quarterly (Box 17)
- Photographs of Parker and Louise S. Parker (his wife) (Box 17)
- UA2012-0062 - Parker's reflections, photographs (Box 17)
- Parker, Carolyn West White, and John C. White correspondence, 1961-1995; 6 folders (Box 18)
  Scope and Contents
  Consists of correspondence exchanged between Harold T. Parker, Carolyn West (White), and John C. White. Parker was the dissertation advisor for both Carolyn West and John C. White.
- Southern Historical Association essays, 1995 November (Box 18)
  Consists of an essay written by Harold Parker and papers about Parker for the annual meeting.
- Obituaries and articles on Harold Parker, 1997-2002 (Box 18)